<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Redeeming the time a sermon preached at Preston in Lancashire, January 4th, 1657 at the funeral of the honourable lady, the Lady Margaret Houghton / by Isaac Ambrose.</title>
            <author>Ambrose, Isaac, 1604-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29590</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11174897</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11174897</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25248)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1434:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Redeeming the time a sermon preached at Preston in Lancashire, January 4th, 1657 at the funeral of the honourable lady, the Lady Margaret Houghton / by Isaac Ambrose.</title>
                  <author>Ambrose, Isaac, 1604-1664.</author>
                  <author>Houghton, Margaret, Lady, d. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Revised and somewhat enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rowland Reynolds ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46544:1"/>
            <p>REDEEMING THE TIME.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>Preſton</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire, January</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1657. at the Funeral of the Honourable Lady, THE LADY MARGARET HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHTON.</p>
            <p>Reviſed, and, ſomewhat Enlarged; and, at the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſome Friends, now publiſhed.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>ISAAC AMBROSE.</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Garſtange</hi> in the ſame County.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rowland Reynalds,</hi> at the Sun and Bible, in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1674.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46544:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46544:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eph. 5.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Redeeming the Time.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle here gives many Leſſons; exhorting 1. to love, <hi>Walk in love, as Chriſt alſo hath loved us:</hi> 2. To fly fornication,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>But fornication, and all uncleaneſs, or covetouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>let it not be once named amongſt you, as becometh Saints.</hi> 3. To avoid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, dear, or familiar converſe with graceleſs men, <hi>Be not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>ye therefore partakers with them; for ye were ſometimes darkeneſs, but now are you light, walk as Children of light.</hi> 4. To walk warily, exactly, circumſpectly, <hi>See then that ye walk circumſpectly, not as fools, but as wiſe.</hi> And this laſt he amplifies from an effect, which teſtifies a circumſpect, exact, and acurate walking, to wit, <hi>Redeeming the time,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I am only to learn you ſome part of this laſt Leſſon; wherein you have 1. The inſtruction it ſelf, <hi>See that you walk circumſpectly.</hi> 2. The amplification of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and that is either from the reaſon binding to it, <hi>not as fools, but as wiſe;</hi> or from the effect teſtifying of it, <hi>Redeeming the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the inſtruction it ſelf, <hi>See that ye walk circumſpectly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, exactly, preciſely;</hi> no word fits the Greek better than this; it comes of two words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifie to go to the extremity of a thing: <hi>we muſt be willing to go to the utmoſt of every Command.</hi> To which purpoſe are thoſe precepts, to be <hi>hot in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> Rev. 3.16. to be <hi>zealous of good works,</hi> Tit. 2.14. to be <hi>fervent in ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.16.</note> Rom. 12.11. to <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait Gate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> Luk. 13.24. with an holy <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to lay hold upon the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.11.</note> Matth. 11.12.<note place="margin">Luke 12.24.</note> But this is not the point I ſhall now inſiſt on.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For the reaſon binding to it, <hi>not as fools, but as wiſe.</hi> It points to us, that <hi>exactneſs, or preciſeneſs in holy walking is a fruit of true Wiſedom. Luther</hi> brings in the men of the World objecting againſt him, <hi>Num tu ſolus ſapis? Num ſolus tu De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places?</hi> What? are you the onely Wiſe man in the World? do you onely pleaſe God? The anſwer was eaſie from this Text, that <hi>exact walking, or a ſtrict converſation, is the fruit of Wiſedom.</hi> But neither is this the point that I ſhall inſiſt on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the effect teſtifying of it, <hi>Redeeming the time.</hi> If I may open the words, 1. By <hi>time</hi> is meant <hi>oppertunity;</hi> which either it taken for the whole courſe of our remaining life, or for ſuch and ſuch particular occaſions as God doth offer to this or that particular duty; and both theſe may be underſtood here. 2. By <hi>Redeeming the time,</hi> is meant either the avoiding of ſome hinderances, which would take us off from the opportunity; or the recompencing of ſome former unfruitfulneſs, which hath been in the former part of our life: or a gaining, ſtreching, improving of time by embracing all the occaſions of doing all the good we can do: and we ſhall diſcover anon, that all theſe may be underſtood here. In the mean time we lay down this Poſition as a neceſſary, fundamental, Evangelical truth, that <hi>time muſt be Redeemed</hi> Look to it all ye that fear God; herein will your ſpiritual Wiſedom, and exact walking appear, even in <hi>Redeeming the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this point, I ſhall 1. give you the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 2. The. 3. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And then come to Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That time muſt be redeemed, the very Heathens confirm it: 'Twas the ſaying of one <hi>Pittacus,</hi> one of the ſeven Wiſe-men, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>know time; loſe not a minute. Theophraſtus</hi> had another ſaying near to this, <hi>Sumptus pretioſiſſimus tempus: time is of pretious coſt. Pliny</hi> ſeeing but his Nephew at leiſure, taking ſome turnes in his walk, was ſo very ſtrict, that he tells him, <hi>Non licet has boras perdere, he ſhould not loſe ſo many precious hours.</hi> When <hi>Titus</hi> the Son of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> who revenged,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46544:3"/>Chriſt's blood on <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> returned victor to <hi>Rome,</hi> remembring one night that had done no good that day, he cryed out to his friends, <hi>Hen perdidi diem! O alas, I have loſt a day!</hi> Little do we think of loſing time, and is not this our ſhame? If ſuch men without God and Chriſt, without Law and Goſpel, without all the promiſes of God and Chriſt in Law or Goſpel, could ſay thus much, how may they riſe up in judgment againſt many of us? But we cite not them, as though we ſtood in need of their learning;<note place="margin">Col. 4.5.</note> the Apoſtles themſelves give it us in charge, <hi>walk in Wiſedom to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that are without,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.15.</note> 
               <hi>redeeming the time, and exhort one another while it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day, leſt any of you be hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin.</hi> And again, <hi>while it is ſaid to day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts.</hi> And, <hi>paſs the time of your ſojourning here with fear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>foraſmuch as ye know that ye were not redeemed with corruptible things,—but with the pretious blood of Chriſt.</hi> q. d. Chriſt redeemed you, and therefore you had need to redeem the time. <hi>For the time paſt of our life may ſuffice us to have wrought the will of the Gentiles.—ſo that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.6, Gal. 10.9.6.</note>—<hi>or no longer ſhould we live the reſt of our time in the fleſh to the luſts of men, but to the will of God.—Let us not be weary in well-doing, for in due ſeaſon we ſhall reap if we faint not; as we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto all men.</hi> It is <hi>Hieroms</hi> ſaying upon theſe words, <hi>O how ſhort is this race of my life? how ſhort is this time now in hand?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Breve vitae Curriculum. <hi>&amp;c. Jeron. l 3.</hi> Comment.</note> 
               <hi>my ſtudying, preaching, writing, correcting, reading, what it is but a gaining or a looſing of my time?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What is it to redeem the time?<note place="margin">John <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> I anſwer, it comprehends theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An avoiding any thing which would hinder us from taking the opportunity. If you ask, what are theſe hinderances? I anſwer, 1. Ignorance; many think they are not in ſo ſtrait a manner to be accountable for time. It is a general opinion of the groſſely ignorant, that if they can but paſs away in time without doing any harm (as they ſay) they are well enough; as if no account of time might be given at all: they are ignorant of this principle, that they <hi>are to improve, and to redeem the time.</hi> 2. Slothfulneſs; this makes men heedleſs, or careleſs of their time: As it is with the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, <hi>Yet a little more ſleep,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>a little more ſlumber, a little more folding of the arms is ſleep.</hi> So it is with the idle perſon, <hi>Let this hour, and this day be ſpent in doing nothing.</hi> O the many golden hours, and days, and years that many thouſands ſpend, and yet cannot give the leaſt account wherein either they have glorified God, or ſerved their generations. 3. Love of fleſhly liberty: Alas, what care they for redeeming time who are ſet on their luſts and liberties to ſin? All the care they have, it is meerly to eat, and drink, and play: ſenſual pleaſures are the whole ſtudy of theſe men, and if they can but enjoy them, let time ſlip away as it will, they never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A recompenſing of ſome former unfruitfulneſs: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath this interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is a redeeming (as it were) of that jewel of time that hath been formerly loſt. As a travailer that hath long ſtayed at an Inne, when he finds the night comming upon him, he mends his pace, and goes as many miles in an hour or two, as he did before in many. This me thinks comes neareſt to the word <hi>Redimo, to redeem,</hi> or to buy back again. It is taken (ſay ſome) from the cuſtom and practice of wiſe Merchants or Tradeſ men, who uie to buy their commodities while fit time of buying ſerves, and while the market holds; and having haply had great loſſes, or formerly ſpent their time idly or unthriftily, they do by their after diligence ſeek to redeem, and (as it were) to buy back again the time that is paſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An embracing of all occaſions for acting graces, and doing good; and this agrees with the reaſon following, <hi>for the dayes are evil.</hi> q. d. Look to your ſelves, for theſe are hard and diſmal times; now is much corruption, and great perſecution, and the opportunity of good is exceedingly ſtraitned; and therefore it is very needful to catch at time, and to lay hold on an opportunity, both to exerciſe graces, and to be doing as much good as you may, while the time permitteth. <hi>I muſt work the works of him that ſent me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>while it is day,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>the night cometh when no man can work:</hi> And,<note place="margin">John 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>yet a little while and the light is with you, walk while ye have the light, leſt dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs come upon you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> And <hi>as we have opportunity, let us do good unto all men, eſpecially to them who are of the houſhold of faith.</hi> Mark theſe ſayings, <hi>while it s called to day; and while the light is with you; and while you have opportunity.</hi> Thus you ſee what it is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46544:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46544:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46544:4"/>
            <p n="3">3. But why muſt <hi>time be redeemed?</hi> what neceſſity for that? I anſwer—</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of time paſt. Alas, many a golden ſeaſon have we loſt, how many hours, and dayes, and months, and years have we ſpent idly, and done little good? Is it not time then to lay hold of every opportunity to redeem time paſt? When God brought us forth into this world, his commands were upon us to work in his vineyard, and to that purpoſe he deſigned to every one his time; <hi>thus many dayes, or months, or years ſhall you every one live, and while you live be imploying theſe and theſe talents; it is my command upon all the ſons of men, in the ſweat of thy face</hi> (i. e. of thy brow, or of thy brain) <hi>ſhall thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>and why then do ye ſtand all the day idle? why are ye not in the work; and eſpecially in the work of the Lord?</hi> Now if this be ſo, that there is ſuch a command, and that we have broke this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand at ſuch a time, and ſuch a time, is it not our duty, and is there not cauſe to redeem the time? A fellow that hath loytered a great part of the day in his buſineſs, and yet muſt needs finiſh his work, will he not toyl and ſweat at it towards night? will he not double his pains, and put all his ſtrength to it? So we, having not onely been ſlack in our buſineſs about Gods ſervice, and ſlow in the way towards Heaven, but even for many yeares having perhaps run in a quite contrary courſe, and done the Devils work, how ſhould we now towards the night of our natural life, and in the concluſion of the ſhort ſpan thereof, ſpare no paines, double our diligence, preſs hard to the price of the high calling with an holy kind of violence, lay hold upon the Kingdom of Heaven, with all zeal, courage, and reſolution labour to redeem paſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is paſt? This our reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of time preſent: It is but a moment on which depends eternal bliſs or woe, if we have loſt time paſt, and if we do loſe time preſent, we may be undone for ever. In this reſpect may we ſay of time, as <hi>Boaz</hi> ſaid to his kinſman concerning <hi>Ruth, If you will redeem it, redeem it:</hi> never think of redeeming it tomorrow,<note place="margin">Ruth. 4.4. 2 Cor. 6.2.</note> or the other day; or hereafter; for no time is properly yours but the preſent time. <hi>Behold now is the accepted time; behold now is the day of ſalvation:</hi> now while I am ſpeaking and you hearing; now ere the night be done or the next day comes on. Oh why ſhould we trifle away the time which is properly ours, and promiſe to our ſelves great things in a time which is none of ours?<note place="margin">Luk 19.42.</note> When Chriſt mourned over <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> he bemoans it thus, <hi>If thou hadſt known, even thou at leaſ in this thy day, the things belonging to thy peace:</hi> So may I mourn over you, if thou hadſt known, even thou <hi>at leſt in this thy day:</hi> when's that? while Miniſters call and you hear, this is your day; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that never heard effectually, let him hear now; it is now high time to awake out of that curſed ſecurity wherein you lie; the Lord is now come near, Chriſt Jeſus is calling, mercy is intreating, and wiſedom is even hoarſe with crying after you, if you loſe this time, this hour of grace, who knows whether ever you ſhall enjoy ſuch another ſeaſon? Oh take time by the forehead! <hi>poſt eſt occaſio calva;</hi> it will be too late ſoon. Now the Lord calls, and now it concerns us to beſtirr our ſelves upon theſe grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe now <hi>are evil dayes;</hi> the very reaſon in the Text: theſe are the laſt times, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>perillous times;</hi> and why perillous?<note place="margin">Tim. 3.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>For men ſhall belevers of their own ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers,</hi> &amp;c. One would think it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Hiſtory than a Prophecie of our dayes. Oh is it not time now, if ever, <hi>to reedeem the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe now are dayes of light: notwithſtanding the evils of ſome or moſt in compariſon, yet many glorious truths do now appear: the Devil, I know, now brings forth his ware, but withal God is now a communicating many bleſſed truths. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of us, our fathers before, and ſince the Reformation were in great darkneſs; the candle of God now ſhines upon this Nation with extraordinary light: And what then? Why therefore it concernes us to <hi>redeem the time:</hi> This is the Apoſtles argument,<note place="margin">Act. 17.30.</note> 
               <hi>The time of this ignorance God winks at but now he commandeth every man every where to repent.</hi> This is another reaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In reſpect of time to come: I ſhall inſtance onely in time of death, and time of judgment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Death is at hand, and then we cannot redeem the time: So the Preacher,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thy hand findeth to doe, doe it with thy might, for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſedom in the grave whither thou goeſt.</hi> q. d. If there be any thing to be done, if there be any duty God requires, doe it in life, for when death ſhall come there ſhall be no more preaching, praying, hearing.<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.18.19.</note> 
               <hi>The grave cannot praiſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46544:5"/>thee, death cannot celebrate thee, they that go down into the pit cannot hope for thy truth: the living, the living he ſhall praiſe thee, as I do this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Our doom for eternity of joyes or woes drawes on apace, and is even at the door. Then I am ſure, account muſt be given for <hi>time,</hi> as well as for all other things. <hi>Come,</hi> will Chriſt ſay, <hi>give an account of thy ſtewardſhip, of all things done in the fleſh, and of every moment of time: how didſt thou ſpend ſuch a day, ſuch a Sabbath? was not ſuch a day ſpent ſinfully, or very unprofitably, and was it ever redeemed?</hi> Here's a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon indeed to force on us this duty. But of this and other reaſons I ſhall ſpeak more in the motives, when I exhort you to it.</p>
            <p>Well then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1.</note> is it ſo, that <hi>time muſt be redeemed?</hi> this may reprove ſeveral ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: as—</p>
            <p n="1">1. The idle; that are ſo far from <hi>redeeming time,</hi> that they are perpetually loſing time. This was the ſin of <hi>Sodom, pride, fulneſs of bread: and abundance of idleneſs, was in her.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note> Give me leave a little to lay open this ſin. Surely this ſin is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all ſins; by doing nothing we ſhall be ſure to learn how to doe ill. It is ſaid of <hi>Rome,</hi> that during the time of their Wars with <hi>Carthage,</hi> and other enemies in <hi>Africa,</hi> they knew not what vice meant; but no ſooner had they got the conqueſt, than through idleneſs they came to ruin. Ruſt you know will fret into the hardeſt Iron, if it be not uſed; ſo vice will infect the beſt heart, if given to idleneſs. Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water is ſooner frozen than the running ſtream; and he that fitteth is more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſleep than he that walketh; ſo the idle man is far more ſubject to temptation than he that is profitably exerciſed. Idleneſs is the Devils ſpecial opportunity; and we have an inſtance in <hi>David's</hi> idleneſs, who at, that time, was ſet on by the Devil to commit other ſins of Adultery and Murder. But this is a ſin that very boyes in Schools can declame againſt; and if it were not that I ſee many amongſt us ſpend their time ſo very unprofitably, I had not once named it. Oh think of it! If a Maſter ſhould ſet a light upon a Candleſtick, and give his ſervant food, and time, and all things convenient wherewith to work, yet when he comes to ſee if his task be finiſhed, he finds that the meat is waſted, the time is ended, the Candle to the very ſocket burned, and little or nothing of the work is furthered, how would ſuch a ſervant excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto his Maſter? And is it not ſo with many of you? God hath given you meat, drink, and time; he hath given you Candle, Fire. and matter; but what have you done? Is not the lamp of your life almoſt conſumed, and yet you have not finiſhed the work that was given you to doe?<note place="margin">Marth. 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>Oh why ſtand ye here all the day idle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The voluptuous: theſe miſpend their time as ill as the former. <hi>They take the timbrel and harp and,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 21.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>rejoyce at the ſound of the organ, they ſpend their dayes in mirth.</hi> They waſte the fat and marrow (as it were) of precious time, even the flower of their age, in froth and folly. Lord, that men ſhould live upon earth, as Liviathan in the Sea, onely to take their ſport and paſtime therein! We have ſeen the ſad Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe of ſome who have led ſuch lives; and I believe ſtill there is a generation of men, that except they be continually exerciſed in variety of pleaſures, they are ſore troubled with <hi>time;</hi> what elſe is the meaning of all thoſe <hi>paſſe-times</hi> (as they call them) but onely a concatenation of ſuch delights as pleaſe the fleſh, that <hi>time</hi> may not be ro tedious weariſome unto them? Little doe theſe men conſider that ſaying of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preſens tempus non effundendi gaudu, ſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulationum <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The preſent time is not for melting into mirth, but for lamentation and mourning; the Devil omits no time to hurt you, for he knowes his time is ſhort; ſtill is he laying his ſnares to intrap mens ſouls; he goes about like a roaring Lion to devour; he roars, and fumes, and flaſhes out fire againſt your Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">Chryſ. <hi>in cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ad</hi> Epheſ. <hi>Ser.</hi> 17.</note> and doe you ſit ſtill, and jovially jeſt it out?</hi> Hark in your ears! <hi>the preſent time is not for mrith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> no, no, the preſent time is for vertuous actions, to do the great buſineſs for which you were born, to mourn, and ſorrow, and ſue out your pardon, and not to ſpend it in jollity, and fleſhly delights. If a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned man had two or three dayes granted him to ſue out his pardon, were that a time for pleaſure and ſports?<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> Surely the ſentence of death is upon all fleſh; <hi>In the day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die;</hi> onely a little uncertain time is granted to ſue out our pardon in the name of Chriſt: why then doe you ſlip away your time ſinfully, and will not redeem it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The godly themſelves: Alas, the beſt are ſhort in this duty of <hi>redeeming the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46544:5"/>time.</hi> Did not the Lord complain againſt his own people,<note place="margin">Jer. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>the Stork in the Heaven knoweth her appointed times; and the Turtle, and the Crane, and the Swallow obſerve the time of their coming, but my people know not the judgment of the Lord.</hi> Certainly God's own people doe not ſo improve, as they ought, thoſe many gracious ſeaſons of love which the Lord affords them. O the omiſſions of Duties, and commiſſions of evils whereof we all ſtand guilty! of how many good hours have we been ill Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands? I ſhall not need to reckon up our times of infancy when we knew nothing, nor of childhood when we knew very little, nor of youth when we knew not much of that we ought to know; but ſince our riper years, yea ſince the time of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy, how prodigal have we been of this precious commodity of <hi>time?</hi> thoſe that keep exact diaries can eaſily tell you, <hi>ſuch an hour loſt, and ſuch an hour ill ſpent; this day I did little good, and the other day I ſinned againſt my God.</hi> If in this caſe I may ſpeak out my own experiences, I muſt needs acknowledge that many and many a day I have loſt ſuch and ſuch an opportunity, and now that evil days come thick up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, wherein I would gladly redeem my days, oh how flow and backward am I as yet in this Heavenly Duty! My dear brethern, I ſhall not onely reprove you, but my ſelf in this: <hi>O why art thou ſo dull, and liſtleſs, and heavy, O my ſoul? Awake, awake! ſtirr up thy ſelf, and with redoubled diligence fall to the work of redeeming time, while yet the time, the day, the ſeaſon, the opportunity of grace, of Heaven, or of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation laſteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Muſt <hi>time be redeemed?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</note> why then let me exhort you by the meekneſs and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs of Chriſt to be in the exerciſe of this Duty. Oh <hi>redeem your time!</hi> avoid all thoſe hinderances that would take you off: recompence your former unfruitfulneſs by after diligence; embrace all occaſions of acting grace, and doing good. I might dilate on all theſe particulars; but I ſhall contract all in theſe very words, <hi>Redeem the time, oh redeem your time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The motives beſides the former reaſons may be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Time is ever on the wing, and ſtayes for no man. The Scripture is very full of this; we meet with many ſimilitudes hinting at the ſudden, inviſible motion of time. <hi>My dayes are ſwifter then a poſt, they fly away;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 9.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>they are paſſed away as the ſwift Ships, as the Eagle that haſteth to the prey.</hi> See how <hi>Job</hi> here multiplies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons, that if we will not learn by the firſt, we might learn by a ſecond, or by a third: Goe we to the land, and there we ſee <hi>time</hi> on the ſpur, in the ſwift riding poſt; goe we to the Sea, and there we ſee <hi>time</hi> upon the wind, in the ſwift ſailing Ship; goe we to the aire, and there we ſee <hi>time</hi> upon the wing, in the ſwift flying Eagle. Hence the Ancients emblem'd <hi>time</hi> with wings, as if it were not onely run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or ſailing, but flying. Oh how ſad it is to ſee men live as if time had leaden heels, and not ſwift wings; or as if <hi>time</hi> would any time ſtay our leaſure, and not be gone. Be not deceived, you that are weary of <hi>time,</hi> either now <hi>redeem it,</hi> or you will one day cry out, <hi>What hath pride profited us? or what good hath riches with our vaunting brought us? All theſe things are paſſed away like a ſhadow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.8, 9.10.11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>and as Poſt that paſſeth by; or as a Ship; — or as a Bird; — or as an Arrow; — even ſo we,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As <hi>time</hi> is ſwift, ſo our time is ſhort. The Heavens indeed are ſaid to be of ſwift motion, but of long continuance; but our <hi>time</hi> is otherwiſe. When the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> propounded divers caſes of conſcience, after ſome anſwers the Apoſtle gives them in this: <hi>But this I ſay, brethren, the time is ſhort;</hi> or <hi>time is cut off:</hi> he alludes to Sea-fearing men that have almoſt done their Voyage, and begin to ſtrike ſail.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.29.</note> Time was in the beginning of the World that men might ſay, I may, by courſe of Nature, live a matter of ſix, or ſeven, or eight, or nine hundred years; but now God hath ſo caſt out the time of our age, that ſo ſoon as we begin our Voyage, we are ready to ſtrike ſail: we have but a little <hi>time;</hi> If I ſhould meaſure it out, what is it but an Ell, a Span, an Inch, a Point? And is it not time then to <hi>redeem the time?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Time is not onely ſwift and ſhort, but nothing, I ſay a very nothing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. As ſome creatures are ſaid to be nothing in compariſon of others. What is the Ant to the Elephant; or the Shrimp to the Whale? what is the whole body of the Earth to the body of the Heavens? So is <hi>our time</hi> as nothing to <hi>all time;</hi> and <hi>all time</hi> is as nothing to Eternity. <hi>David</hi> that found out a ſhort di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46544:6"/>of his <hi>time</hi> conſidered abſolutely,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.5.</note> or in it ſelf, <hi>Behold thou haſt made my dayes as an hand-breath;</hi> yet he could find out no dimenſion: little enough for his time compared with God, <hi>Mine age is as nothing before thee.</hi> God's being conſiſts in one <hi>Eternal</hi> now; but mans <hi>time</hi> is divided into paſt, preſent, and to come; three nothings, which being added together amount in the total to this Sum, <hi>Mine age is as nothing before thee.</hi> Oh that we would conſider of this language of the Holy Ghoſt! were it not enough, think you, to put us on this Duty of improving and trading our time while the time is ours, and while this ſhort time laſteth?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though <hi>time</hi> be ſwift and ſhort, and as nothing in compariſon, yet is it a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity more precious than the Gold of <hi>Ophir.</hi> If herein we might hear loſt Souls to utter themſelves, Oh what would they ſay? or what would they give for a little of that little time they had on earth? If the Lord by Divine and Extraordinary diſpenſation would but grant them one months time to come hither again, and to make a new trial, do you think they would not prize this grant? would they not eſteem that little ſhort Golden ſeaſon of grace at an high and mighty rate? Would they not make uſe of every opportunity to lay hold of Heaven, and to eſcape thoſe fires wherein now they are burning, frying, and flaming? O yes! if you would then tempt them, ſaying, <hi>Come, ſpend this hour merrily;</hi> would they not anſwer; <hi>alas, we have but one months time to live here in this World, and then we muſt either to Hell again, or if we improve our time well, we muſt to Heaven; and what? ſhall we trifle away this time of trial and of grace in offending God? ſhall we caſt away our Souls again to gratifie you, or to pleaſe our own fleſh, for ſo little a time as we have now to live? Oh God forbid! avoid Satan! avoid all Temptations! welcome now all thoſe meſſengers of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that will bring us the glad tidings, the tenders, the offers of Chriſt and of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! let not one ſand in the hour-glaſs run, but let us be doing ſome good; let this hour be ſpent in prayer, and the next in meditation, and the next in hearing of God's Word, and the next in the exerciſe of this and that grace, and ſo on; but not one hour in ſin.</hi> Why ſurely thus would they prize and improve <hi>the time,</hi> that know by woful experience what it is to loſe <hi>the time.</hi> And by this we may gueſs the worth of <hi>time;</hi> oh it is pretious ſo pretious that if all the Earth were turned into Gold, it could not purchaſe one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of it. Me thinks this motive ſhould work, and now that we have a little time, it ſhould prevail with us to <hi>redeem the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Our <hi>time</hi> hath been a very ſinful <hi>time.</hi> Ah my brethren, think over your Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, unbelief, worldlineſs, covetouſneſs, pride, malice, luſts, lukewarmneſs, impatience, diſcontentedneſs, vain-glory, ſelf love, wandring and wicked imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: in a word, all your pollutions, diſtempers, eſtrangedneſs from God in the time of your unregeneracy; oh were not thoſe ſinful, abominable, and rebellious times: or be it ſo that your gracious God hath ſince thoſe times wrought in you ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually his ſaving grace, have you not ſince, then loſt your firſt love, or at leaſt grown remiſs, and cold, and lukewarm in it? Say then, ſpeak out your hearts and tell me, is it not time now to remember from whence you are fallen, and to repent, and to do your firſt works? Bleſſed Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> hath a ſaying, that <hi>if it were poſſible that any uncomfortable paſſion were incident to a glorified Saint in Heaven, he would be ſorry, and tranſported with extream anger and indignation againſt himſelf that he was not a meer greedy ingroſſer (as it were) and improver of time for doing excellently upon Earth, and that every hour, eſpecially after his Converſion, was not Crowned with ſome rare and more remarkable exploit, with ſome more ſpecial and noble ſervice for the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of that moſt bountiful and ever-bleſſed God, who hath now honored him with ſuch unſpeakable glory in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> But if no ſuch paſſion is in glorified Saints, I am ſure we have all cauſe enough to loath our ſelves in our own fight for our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and for our abominations. O come, let this be a motive to ſpur us on, and to quicken us in this duty of <hi>Redeeming the time,</hi> becauſe <hi>our dayes were evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The Scriptures ſpeak of a remarkable ſet time of grace, <hi>a time of viſitation,</hi> Luke 19.44. <hi>a time of Salvation,</hi> 2 Cor, 6.2. <hi>a time whileſt God may be found,</hi> Pſal. 32.6. <hi>a time when he holds out the Golden Seepter.</hi> Eſther. 5.2. a time wherein the Fountain runneth, and the ſpirit proclameth, <hi>Ho, every on that thirſteth come ye to the Waters,</hi> Iſa. 55.1. Thus <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had her time; and all the ſeveral Churches in <hi>Aſia</hi> had their time; and now <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have their time; and if we miſ-improve this time, and walk unworthy of this grace and Goſpel of Chriſt, this time will have an end,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.11.</note> this Sun will go down at Noon, and ſet upon our heads. <hi>This
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46544:6"/>day, if you will hear my voice harden not your hearts,</hi> ſaid God to Iſrael; but they hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their hearts, and therefore <hi>God ſware to them in his wrath that they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into his reſt.</hi> If it be ſo with us as it was with Iſrael in the wilderneſs, we doe not know but this very day the Lord may clap an Oath upon our heads, that we ſhall never enter into his reſt. Oh then that we would learn of the Ant, that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her meat in the Summer time! Oh that while we have this time of grace, we would redeem the time in praying, reading, hearing, meditating, and treaſuring up the things belonging to our peace! This time is a ſet-time that haſtens away: and we cannot with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> bid the Sun ſtand ſtill. O then let us ſay, <hi>This is our time, and therefore what we will do for our Souls, we will do it now.</hi> Surely better it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem it now, than to wiſh in pain and torment for the time again when it is paſt redemption.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The time, is a coming, yea it is near, even at the door, when <hi>time</hi> ſhall be no more. This is the voice of the ſeventh Angel,<note place="margin">Rev. 10.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>And the Angel which I ſaw ſtanding upon the Sea and upon the Earth, lifted up his hand to Heaven, and ſware by him that liveth for ever and ever, that there ſhould be time no longer.</hi> Who was this? a man? no, <hi>an Angel:</hi> and what, did he ſay it? no, <hi>he ſware it:</hi> how ſware it, by himſelf? no, he ſware it <hi>by him that lives for ever:</hi> and what? that time ſhould be little? no, it ſhould be no longer, <hi>time ſhould be no more.</hi> Needs muſt this <hi>time</hi> come, that hath all theſe circumſtances to confirm it. And what if this <hi>time</hi> ſhould come even in your <hi>time?</hi> what if now the ſeventh Angel ſhould lift up his hand to Heaven, and take this Oath? If this <hi>time</hi> be far off as to the general Judgment (which I cannot think) yet ſure I am, and without all peradventure, that it is not far off to thee and me. It may be before this year, this month, this week, this night be done, that God may ſay to his Angel, <hi>Go to ſuch a man, and ſuch a woman, I will give them no more time; bring them hither, and here let them give an account what they have done with all their time, for I muſt have a reckoning of all time paſt.</hi> And then comes in, <hi>Imprimis,</hi> ſo much time in Drinking and Revelling; <hi>Item</hi> ſo much time in Idling, Sporting, playing, &amp;c. <hi>Oh,</hi> will God ſay, <hi>were theſe things I gave you time for? no, no, it was for Heaven and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation you had your time; and if that time be miſ-improved, away, away time, and now enter Eternity upon theſe Souls.</hi> Is not here a motive to make us look about us? Oh my brethren, now, now if ever, redeem the time, for anon time will be gone, and then ſucceeds eternity, eternity, eternity.</p>
            <p>But what are the means for <hi>redeeming time?</hi> I anſwer.—</p>
            <p>They are ſo many, that I may have no time to enumerate the Particulars; ſhall we inſtance in ſome? you muſt pray, read, hear the Word, meditate, and watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your hearts with extraordinary induſtry; mortifie your members which are upon the Earth, as pride, covetouſneſs, luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> grow up in grace, clear up your eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt that day when all ſhall ſtand naked before that great and glorious Judge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And theſe, and all other Duties (of which anon) muſt be done while the day laſteth. Here's a great work, and a little time; doth it not concern you to beſtir your ſelves? If a man have much to write, and but a little Paper to write on, he muſt write ſmall, and thick, and cloſe as ever he can: So muſt you do. I verily believe there's not one Soul amongſt us but he may find out hundreds and thouſands of ſins to repent him of; he may find out many and many a Particular Duty that he ſhould be exerciſed in from morning to evening, and from evening to morning; ſo that 'tis a wonder how he can ſpare any time at all for any thing elſe. Well then, up and be doing; loſe not a minute, but be in the uſe and exerciſe of ſome of theſe Dutys. Theſe are the means, and in the uſe of theſe means you may (by the Lords help and grace concurring) <hi>redeem your time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Objection I would remove. <hi>It may be the day of grace is done, the gate of mercy is already ſhut; and if ſo, how is it poſſible for me to redeem the time?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer—</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Conceſſion. I believe there is a day of grace indeed, and if that Sun ſet, it will never, never riſe again. <hi>If thou hadſt known, even thou at leaſt in this thy day, the things belonging to thy peace, but now are they hid from thine eyes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 19.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> q. d. Now is the gate of mercy ſhut, there is no means of grace or Salvation for ever hereafter to be hoped for. As there is no Market or Fair-day that laſteth alwayes; if the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try will not come in, the Tradeſ-man will at laſt put up his wares: So the Lord's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46544:7"/>ſtanding may be open, and his ſhop ſet wide for ſuch and ſuch a time; but if Souls will not come in, and buy without mony and without price, he will at laſt put up his wares (all his jewels of grace) and then be gone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though it be true that there is a day of grace, and that this day may ſet; yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of us the Miniſters of Chriſt, we cannot determine it; and therefore ſo long as you live we call ſtill, <hi>oh repent! oh redeem your time!</hi> I may add, in reſpect of your ſelves, <hi>it is not in you to know the times and ſeaſons which God hath put in his own power.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note> And the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Faith ſtanding in force on you ſo long as you live, and thereforce you are ſtill to look to your Duty of <hi>redeeming the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It may be this day, this night, this Sermon, this very hour may be thy day of grace. Hearken! is not Chriſt's Spirit now a knocking? is not Chriſt himſelf now offering mercy to thy Soul? <hi>O ye ſons of men that have miſ-improved your time, will ye now at leaſt in this your day he wiſe to Salvation? why now I call to your hearts; now I command you to open your everlaſting doors, that I, the King of Glory, may come in; oh let this be the time of love! Come, give me your hearts, and now redeem the time.</hi> Away, away with all objections, ſcruples, cavils that may hinder this Duty, and now, even now, hearken to this voice of Chriſt, or of the Spirit of Chriſt, that your Souls may live.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Muſt <hi>time be redeemed?</hi> Then for ſome Rules or Directions how we muſt redeem it.</p>
            <p>Rule 1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>A void we every thing that would hinder us from taking the opportunity.</hi> What thoſe things are you have heard before; as ignorance, ſloth, and love of fleſhly liberty. Many other particulars might be enumerated, but chiefly and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially foregoe we theſe.</p>
            <p>Rule. 2. <hi>Repent we of all former miſ-improvings of our time.</hi> There is no other way of recompenſing former unfruitfulneſs but by repentance and after diligence. This is the ſcond table after ſhipwrack; in this way we may redeem, or buy back again the time that is paſt. The very word <hi>reſipiſcentia</hi> ſignifies <hi>to be wiſe again,</hi> after all our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer follies. Oh that ever any ſhould be ſo unworthy as to decry this godly-Goſpel-gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Rule.</p>
            <p>Rule 3. <hi>Live we every day as if every day were the laſt day we had to live.</hi> This Rule or direction is ſo comprehenſive, that I muſt needs break it into particulars. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then I were to begin this day, and that I look't on this day as the laſt day of my life, how ſhould I redeem my time; or ſpend this day? I anſwer.—</p>
            <p n="1">1. My firſt and morning-thoughts ſhould be on God, or on ſomething in order to his ſervice.<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.6.</note> 
               <hi>My Soul waiteth for the Lord more than they that watch for the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 23.2.</note>—<hi>O Lord be gracious to me. I have waited for thee, be thou my arm every Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 59.16.</note>—<hi>I will ſing of thy power, I will ſing aloud of thy mercy in thy Morning.—It is good to give thanks unto the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>and to ſing praiſes unto thy name, O moſt high, to ſhew forth thy loving kindneſs in the Morning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.17.</note>—<hi>How pretious are thy thoughs unto me O God, when I awake, I am ſtill with thee.</hi> Now theſe Morning-thoughts may be ſpent either in a way of Meditation,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.</note> or of Prayer; and my Duties lie in both.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhould meditate. I ſhall not determine whether Morning or Evening may be more ſuitable for ſet, deliberate, and ſolemn meditation? onely this I affirm, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſolemn, or an occaſional meditation is a Morning-duty. In ſome ſort medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and prayer ſhould ever go together;<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.1, 2.3.</note> and <hi>David</hi> thus, couples them, <hi>Give ear to my words, O Lord, conſider my meditation, hearken to the voice of my cry.—My voice ſhalt thou hear in the Morning, O Lord, in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee.</hi> Now theſe Morning-meditations (if occaſional or ejaculatory) may be on ſuch Objects as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon my firſt waking I may think on that Morning of my Reſurrection, when the Lord will awake me from the duſt; it is but a while till the trump ſhall ſound, <hi>Awake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.19.</note> 
               <hi>and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt, for thy dew is as the dew of herbs; and then ſhall the earth caſt out her dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon ſight of the Morning-ſun I may think on that Sun of Righteouſneſs that enlightens Heaven. The Sun that ſhines on me was only created for this nether World, and yet how glorious is it? Oh then what light is there in that City above, that <hi>hath no need of Sun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Re. 21.23.</note> 
               <hi>or Moon, or Star, for the glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Upon the putting on of my apparel I may think on that garment of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs where with my ſoul either is or ſhould be cloathed. Alas! what is this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46544:7"/>Robe but a Rag, or at beſt an excrement of dead worms, of which I have little reaſon to be proud? But my Souls Robe is as a garment cut out of the Sun,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.1.</note> and put upon me. <hi>And there appeared a great wonder in Heaven, a woman cloathed with the Sun.</hi> Oh that I may be cloathed with that Sun of Righteouſneſs, or with that Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Son of God, that I may appear before God as I am in him, pure and ſpotleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall not inſtance in any other objects of my Mornings meditation; onely if I find my ſpirit moſt active and fit for meditation at ſuch a time. <hi>I</hi> ſhould then go on, and ſpare more time for ſet, deliberate, and ſolemn meditations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I</hi> ſhould pray; and to this Duty <hi>I</hi> may joyn the reading of the Word. That this is a mornings Duty the Scripture is expreſs:<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>In the Morning will I direct my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer unto thee, and will look up.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 88.13.</note>—<hi>And in the morning ſhall my prayer prevent thee.—And evening, and morning, and at noon will I pray, and crie aloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.17.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſhall hear my voice.</hi> It is true, that Prayer and reading of the Word are two diſtinct exerciſes, yet that they mutually help one another is moſt manifeſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently are fit to be joyned together; for the word miniſters matter of prayer, and is the ground of our petition, who have no promiſe to be heard, unleſs we ask ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's word, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14. And the fitneſs of the morning for theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes is evident, not only becauſe the firſt of <hi>time</hi> belongs unto God, but alſo the heart being then moſt free from worldly thoughts, it is therefore fitteſt for Holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes; and withal, when in the beginning of the day the heart of man is ſeaſoned with Holineſs, and with the fear of God, he ſhall find himſelf the better fitted to walk humbly with God all the day after.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All the reſt of the day till evening ſhould <hi>I</hi> ſpend my time in the Duties of my particular calling, nor know I the leaſt reaſon why any man in the world, high or low, rich or poor, ſhould be herein exempted. <hi>Adam muſt not eat his bread with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſweat and labour. Abel was a keeper of ſheep. Cain a tiller of the ground.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Jabal was a Tent-maker. Jubal the father of ſuch as handle the harp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.2, 20.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Tubal Cain an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer in Braſs and Iron.</hi> All the the Patriarchs of Iſrael were but Shepherds; and Jeſus Chriſt himſelf was a plain Carpenter.</p>
            <p>But you may object, may I not herein loſe my time as to God's ſervice? One would think, if this were my laſt day I ſhould do no other work but pray, or hear, or read, or meditate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I anſwer—</p>
            <p n="1">1. I grant there are ſuch times wherein God calls us extraordinarily to ſuch ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Duties all the day long; as either in afflictions felt or feared, or in ſome ſpecial mercies expected or received. And there are thoſe times we call the Lords dayes, wherein we are to do no work ordinarily but of a Spiritual nature And there are ſuch times wherein God holds forth an opportunity of exerciſing graces, or of doing good; and ſo to embrace the occaſion is one piece or part of our redeeming time.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>As we have opportunity let us do good to all men.</hi> And <hi>your care of me hath flouriſhed again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.10.</note> (ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Philippians</hi>) <hi>but ye lacked opportunity.</hi> It ſeems their care for the Apoſtle was intermitted for a ſeaſon, for want of oppertunity to ſend unto him, but now they put forth again as flowers in Spring. I doubt not but in ſuch caſes as theſe, we may, and muſt for the time diſpenſe with our particular callings. Yet.—</p>
            <p n="2">2. In my ordinary conſtant daily courſe I am to be in the exerciſe of my Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular calling, with which I may either mingle ſome actings of grace, or ejaculatory Duties, as ſuddenly to look up to Heaven, and to behold the face of God, to whom I am to approve my ſelf in my particular calling; or if they claſh, I am ſolely to follow my particular calling, and to leave other Spiritual actings till their appointed ſeaſon. Nor do I herein decline God's ſervice. For 1. I follow my calling out of an awful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the eye, preſence, and command of God, who hath ſaid. <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour:</hi> Yea I do what I do in civil buſineſs as the work of Chriſt, ſo that I may ſay at that time <hi>now am I about the work of God, and of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Seeing my ſelf thus working for him, I may eaſily apprehend that for that time I honour God as much, nay more by the meaneſt ſervile worldly act, than if I ſhould ſpend all that time in Prayer, Meditation, or any other Spiritual employment to which I had no call at ſuch a time. It is noted therefore, by ſome, of <hi>Peter's</hi> Wives Mother, that when Chriſt had healed her of her Feaver, ſhe ſat not down at Table with Chriſt in Communion with him, which (no queſtion) was ſweet, but <hi>ſhe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46544:8"/>unto them</hi> (i.e.) ſhe ran to and fro, and ſerved him, and acted for him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe ſhewed more love,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.15.</note> and gave him more honour, than if at that time ſhe had enjoyed Communion with him in a nearer way.</p>
            <p>But I hear others object, May I not take up ſome little of this time in recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? what, muſt I alwayes be on my calling? Is there not <hi>a time to every purpoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3.1, 4.</note> 
               <hi>a time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer: There is indeed a time to recreate; but that time is then, I ſay onely then, when our bodies or minds are wearied with our other employments. O what a ſad thing it is to ſee many ſpend a whole day, it may be a whole week in unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinful recreations! What, is this to <hi>redeem the time?</hi> or dare I thus ſpend the laſt day of my life in this world? Surely, God's people that make conſcience of their Duties, ſhould not meddle at any time with recreations (though in themſelves law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) without true cauſe, and a juſt calling thereunto; nor ſhould they uſe them any longer, nor to any other end, but only to quicken their minds, or to revive their bodies, that ſo they may return with ſome lightſomneſs and alacrity to their callings again. He that ſpends his time laviſhly in recreations, is like him whoſe Garments are made of fringes, and his meat nothing but ſauces. I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt recreations lawfully uſed, but God forbid that we ſhould trifle away our time (more worth than worlds) upon fooliſh, vain, empty, end unneceſſary toyes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The evening ſhould be cloſed up with ſpiritual duties. If you ask what Duties? I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The evening is a time for prayer, <hi>Let my prayer be ſet forth before thee as incenſe, and the lifting up of my hands as the evening ſacrifice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2.</note> To this of prayer I joyn read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture, and good books; for it is fit to cloſe up the day with the ſame du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wherewith we began it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The evening was <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s time for meditation: <hi>And Iſaac went out to meditate in the field at the even-tide.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24.63.</note> It may be in this Duty the morning is not ſo ſeaſonable for ſome tempers; but ſhall the evening paſs without ſome ſpiritual Holy meditations? Some conceive the evening to be the very ſeaſon of ſet and deliberate meditation; and in this caſe how fruitful might I be in the uſe of that Ordinance of <hi>Looking unto Jeſus, as he carries on the great work of our Salvation from firſt to laſt?</hi> O that this Duty of meditation, either on that, or any other ſpiritual ſubject, were not ſo neglected as it is by Chriſtians themſelves!<note place="margin">Jod. 1.8.</note> The Lord gave <hi>Joſhua</hi> a charge, that he ſhould <hi>mediate on his Law day and night;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> and <hi>David's</hi> character of the bleſſed man is, that <hi>his delight is in the Law of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 63.6.</note> 
               <hi>and in his Law doth he meditate day and night.</hi> And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s own practice was to <hi>remember God upon his bed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>and to meditate on him in the night-watches.</hi> And <hi>Paul's</hi> charge to <hi>Timothy</hi> was to <hi>meditate upon ſpiritual things, and to give himſelf wholly to them.</hi> Or if you'l have another proof for the evening-ſeaſon, not only was it <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s time, but <hi>David's</hi> time, <hi>Mine eyes prevent the night-watches, that I might meditate in thy word.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.148.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The evening is a ſeaſon for ſelf-examination. This is another glorious ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which many Chriſtians uſe occaſionally, and againſt ſome good time; but to ſet ſome time apart for this every evening, and that in conſcience, as they do for read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word, and Prayer, where is the Chriſtian almoſt to be found? I am ſure it was <hi>David</hi>'s charge. <hi>Commune with your own heart upon your bed, and be ſtill.</hi> And agreeable to this was his practice,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>I call to remembrance my ſong in the night,</hi> I <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with my own heart, and my ſpirit made diligent ſearch. Chryſoſtom</hi> on theſe words of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 77.6.</note> 
               <hi>What means this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>commune with your own hearts upon your bed?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poſt doenam, Chryſoſt. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. in. <hi>Pſa. 4.4.</hi>
               </note> thus anſwers himſelf, <hi>after ſupper-time, when ye are going to ſleep, and are ready to ly down on bed, and have great quiet and ſilence, without the preſence or diſturbance of any, then erect a tribunal for the conſcience.—And when neither friend diſturbs you,<note place="margin">Docuerant nos ſaepe patres no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, &amp;c. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voth. tom. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> nor ſervants provoke you, nor multitudes of buſineſs do preſs upon you, then take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your life, what you have done in the day-time before.</hi> And <hi>Dorotheus</hi> layes it down as a rule which <hi>the Chriſtians of his time had learned of their fore-fathers, that in the evening they ſhould queſtion themſelves how they had paſſed the day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biblioth. Pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
               </note> Oh that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians now would Sum up their accounts at the foot of every page, I mean, that they would call themſelves to ſcrutiny every evening when they are ready to compoſe themſelves to ſleep, as to the little Images of Death!</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46544:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. The evening is a ſeaſon to conſider my Priviledges in Chriſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.</note> When <hi>David</hi> was ready for his Bed, <hi>I will lay me down in peace, and ſleep</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>for thou Lord only makeſt me dwell in ſafety.</hi> See how he ſpeaks of <hi>peace, and reſt, and ſleep, and ſafety:</hi> all theſe were Priviledges. Me thinks it is a ſweet concluſion of a good dayes work, and a bleſſed farewel to the World if this evening were my laſt, and that immediately I muſt go to God, to conſider of ſome of thoſe glorious Priviledges in God and Chriſt. I might inſtance in my <hi>peace, and reſt, and ſleep, and ſafety,</hi> by vertue of a promiſe, or covenant of Grace; or I might inſtance in my <hi>Election, Redemption, Reconciliation, Adoption, Sanctification, Glorification:</hi> But becauſe theſe are commonly handled; <hi>and our communion with God and Chriſt; and the ſpirit of Chriſt</hi> is the moſt raviſhing Priviledge in this World, my ſoul carries me out for the preſent to pitch on this.<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> communion God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</note> One of our Worthies hath writ eminenly on it; and for a taſte of his excellent work, the ſweeting of my laſt thoughts with ſuch an excellent ſubject, I ſhall contract it thus,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I would conſider my communion with God the Father in love. This the Father pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly fixes upon the Saints; and this they are immediately to eye him in,</hi> God is love. <hi>Chriſtians walk of times with exceeding troubled hearts concerning the thoughts of the Father towards them; they are well perſwaded of the Lord Chriſt and his good will; the difficulty lies in what is their acceptance with the Father, what is his heart towards them? Now here is the work of the Goſpel to diſcover the love of the Father: this is the will of God, that he may alwayes be eyed as being, kind, tender, loving, yea as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Spring of all gracious Communications and fruits of love; and when Chriſtians apprehend this, that</hi> God is love, <hi>and ſo reſt upon him, and delight in him as ſuch, then have they communion with the Father in love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now for the exerciſe of my ſoul in this bleſſed communion, the directions are ſuch as theſe.—</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I muſt eye the Father as</hi> Love. I <hi>muſt not look on him as one that is alwayes angry; but as one moſt kind and tender in himſelf, and as one that hath had thoughts of kindneſs towards his Saints from everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I <hi>muſt ſo eye the love of the Father, as to receive it by faith;</hi> I <hi>muſt believe this love of God as for my ſelf. Certainly his love is not mine, nor will it be mine in the ſweetneſs of it, untill it be ſo received. Either</hi> I <hi>muſt know it, aſſent to it, embrace it, and have all my affections filled with it, or it will be in vain as to my Communion with God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This love muſt have its proper fruit and efficacy upon my heart in a return of love to him again. To this purpoſe God loves, that he may be beloved: this is the return that he demands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23.26.</note> My ſon, give me thy heart, <hi>thy affections, thy love O the Priviledge of Saints! they have meat to eat that the World knows not of they have cloſe communion and fellowſhip with the Father; they deal with him in the interchange of love; ſo that every one of them may ſay.</hi> If I have hatred in the World, I will goe where I am ſure of love; though all others are hard to me, yet my Father is tender and full of compaſſion, I will goe to him, and ſatisfie my ſelf in him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I <hi>would conſider of my communion with God the Son in grace. So the Apoſtle ſpeaking of our communion with him as Mediator, concludes his Epiſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.23.</note> The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all. <hi>Not to mention any other grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>but his perchaſed grace of juſtification, or acceptation with God the directions for this Communion are ſuch as theſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.24.</note>—</p>
            <p>I <hi>muſt eye Chriſt's doings and ſufferings; not as for himſelf but for his Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>and for their Righteouſneſs.</hi> He was made under the Law,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4, 5.</note> that we might receive the adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sons, <hi>And</hi> he bare our ſins in his body on the Tree.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>This was the end of Chriſt's life and death, to work out a compleat Righteouſneſs for believers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 3.18.</note>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>as to a perfect acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>muſt approve of this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt as that alone which is abſolutely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, and able to make me acceptable before God. Of this</hi> I <hi>am convinced, that if</hi> I <hi>die this night, there is a neceſſity of a Righteouſneſs, wherewith</hi> I <hi>muſt appear before God; and if</hi> I <hi>have nothing to commend me unto God but my own Righteouſneſs, oh how ſhould</hi> I <hi>appear before his glory? there is no other name but Chriſt whereby</hi> I <hi>can be ſaved; and there is no other Righteouſneſs but Chriſts whereby</hi> I <hi>can be juſtified.</hi> Surely ſhall one ſay, in the Lord have I Righteouſneſs and ſtrength.<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I <hi>muſt make an actual commutation with the Lord Jeſus as to my ſins, and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. And to that purpoſe</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I <hi>muſt hearken to the voice of Chriſt calling me to him with my burthen,</hi> Come to me thou poor ſoul with thy guilt of ſin, for that is mine; this agreement I made with my Father from all Eternity, that I ſhould come, and take thy ſins and bear them away; they were my lot, give me thy burden, give me all thy ſins, thou knoweſt not what to do with them, I know how to diſpoſe of them well enough, ſo that God ſhall be glorified, and thy ſoul delivered.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46544:9"/>call I muſt lay down my ſins at the Croſs of Chriſt upon his ſhoulders. This is faiths great and bold adventure upon the grace, faithfulneſs, and truth of Chriſt, to ſtand by the Croſs, and ſay,</hi> Ah! he is bruiſed for my ſins, and wounded for my tranſgreſſions, and the chaſtiſement of my peace is upon him: He is thus made ſin for me; here I give up my ſins to him that is able to bear them; he requries at my hands that I ſhould be content to throw my ſins upon him, and to this I conſent.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Having thus by faith given up my ſins to Chriſt,</hi> I <hi>muſt draw nigh, and take from him that Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which he hath wrought out for me: To this purpoſe he tenders himſelf and his Righteouſneſs to be my Righteouſneſs before God; and by my acceping of it,</hi> I <hi>compleat this bartering and exchange of faith, and come into communion with Jeſus Chriſt, as to my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation with God by grace.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21.</note> He was made ſin for us, that we might become the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I <hi>would conſider of my communion with the holy Ghoſt in comfort.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14.26.</note> 
               <hi>We read uſually in the Goſpel that</hi> he is the Comforter.<note place="margin">John 15.26.</note> 
               <hi>Oh the condeſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt! he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly proceedeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>or comes forth from the Father to be our Comforter; he knew what we were, and what would be our dealings with him; he knew we would grieve him, provoke him; quench his motions, defile his dwelling place, and yet he would come to be our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter. Now for my communion with the holy Ghoſt herein the directions are theſe.</hi>—</p>
            <p n="1">1. I <hi>muſt ask him of the Father in the name of Jeſus Chriſt. This is the daily work of Believers; they look upon, and conſider the holy Ghoſt as promiſed to be ſent, and in this promiſe they know lies all their grace, peace, mercie, and comfort; for by him ſo promiſed are theſe things communicated.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>O then how ſhould</hi> I <hi>ask him of the Father, who is as ready to beſtow him on me, as</hi> I <hi>am to give my children bread?</hi> If ye being evil know how to give good gifs unto your children, how much more ſhall your Heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that ask him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If comfort come,</hi> I <hi>muſt learn to act faith diſtinctly on the Holy Ghoſt, as the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate efficient cauſe of all my comfort. It may be the Spirit is given, and be tenders, or adminiſters conſolations, but then I do not conſider him as the Comforter, why ſurely this grievs him: a lively faith will take notice of his kindneſs; upon every work of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that</hi> I <hi>receive,</hi> I <hi>ſhould write this Motto,</hi> This is from the Holy Ghoſt, he is my Comforter, and the God of all my conſolation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I <hi>muſt return praiſe and thanks, and honour, and glory, and bleſſings to him on the account of thoſe comforts</hi> I <hi>receive from him. When</hi> I <hi>feel my ſelf warmed with joy, ſupported with peace, or eſtabliſhed in obedience,</hi> I <hi>ſhould then aſcribe to him the praiſe that is his due. And this praiſing of him is no ſmall part of my communion with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Say now, is not here a Priviledge worthy of my conſideration? would not a thought of this,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.54, 25.</note> and my acting in this, leave a ſweet favour in my ſoul when I am going to my Bed as to my grave?<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> could ſay, <hi>Thy ſtatutes have been my ſong in the houſe of my Pilgrimage;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 149.5.</note> I <hi>have remembred thy name O Lord in the night.</hi> And <hi>my ſoul ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>and my mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lips.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 35.10.</note> Ay, but when muſt this be? He anſwers, <hi>When</hi> I <hi>remember thee upon my Bed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.8:</note> 
               <hi>and meditate on thee in the night-watches.</hi> And he faſtens it as a Duty upon all Saints,<note place="margin">Pſal: 77: 6:</note> 
               <hi>Let the Saints be joyful in glory, let them ſing aloud upon their beds.</hi> And the Church reſolves upon it, <hi>With my ſoul have I deſired thee in the night, and with my ſpirit within me will</hi> I <hi>ſeek thee early.</hi> Surely <hi>it is God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Elihu who giveth ſongs in the night.</hi> And <hi>in the night</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>his ſong ſhall be with me.</hi> And 'twas a bleſſed remedy to his heavy Soul, <hi>I call to remembrance my ſong in the night.</hi> Oh that with ſuch thoughts and conſiderations of my communion with God, and Chriſt, and the ſpirit of Chriſt, for of ſome other Priviledge, I might every night go to my Bed! for then like the Philomele ſhould I ſing in the night; yea then would <hi>my Soul be ſatisfied as with Marrow and fatneſs, and my Mouth would praiſe him with joyful lips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might inſtance in many other duties which would then be ſeaſonable, but theſe are the main; and if this day were my laſt day, or if this night I muſt ſleep my laſt in this world, yet I ſhould comfortably hope that in the doing of theſe duties in a ſpiritual manner, I had in good meaſure <hi>redeemed my time;</hi> and that <hi>when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake,</hi> though I never awake till the Reſurrection day, yet then ſhould I ſee God face to face, and <hi>I ſhould be ſatisfied with his likeneſs:</hi> Pſal. 17.15.</p>
            <p>I have now done; only before we part, I would ſay ſomething of the deceaſed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as to our edification, and ſo an end.</p>
            <p>You know I have been ſparing in this way, becauſe of many abuſes, and eſpecially becauſe all promiſcuouſly look for praiſes at their death, howſoever they ſpend their life. But now God hath removed me from this paſtoral charge, and I ſhall not here perform many of theſe laſt offices of love, probably never more than this; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at this time I ſhall crave your patience and attentions to what may be ſpoken without any prejudice to truth or harm to you.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46544:9"/>
            <p>The Duty I am preſſing on you, is to <hi>redeem the time;</hi> and this I believe of the deceaſed party, that ſhe <hi>redeemed her time.</hi> I ſhall not ſpeak of her Birth, Education, Progeny, Nobility: <hi>Stemmata quid faciunt?</hi> Alas! what's all this to a Funeral-Sermon? Nor ſhall I ſpeak of her youth or flouriſhing time; as I am a ſtranger to it, ſo I believe ſhe had, or might have her fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in that time. The temptations of honour, riches, proſperity, and youth are ſtronger than moſt imagine; and therefore prayed <hi>David, Remember not the ſins of my youth: Pſal.</hi> 25.7. and all that are honourable may pray, <hi>Remember not the ſins of my honour, nobility, and greatneſs in the world.</hi> For my part I ſhall not take notice of theſe things, or of thoſe times, but rather ſpeak of her <hi>redeeming the time,</hi> ſince that time that forſaking the World in great meaſure, ſhe gave up her ſelf in a more retired and ſolitary way to ſerve her God.</p>
            <p>Now then if here I begin; She hath for theſe many years <hi>redeemed her time;</hi> as thus,
<list>
                  <item>1. In life,</item>
                  <item>2. In Death.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In life, it will appear in her general and particular calling.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, ordinarily every Morning and every evening ſhe was exerciſed in thoſe duties of Meditation and Prayer: This was her courſe, not by fits and ſtarts, but daily, in her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Walks, or private Chamber, ſhe ſpent both her early and later houres in Communion with God. Nor ſpeak I this by report onely, for of her goodneſs and bounty ſhe was pleaſed every Spring to invite me to her Houſe, and by this meanes I was acquainted with her conſtant courſe. Indeed I was the more willing to embrace her welcome, becauſe her Houſe ſeemed to me as <hi>a Colledge for Religion,</hi> or as a retirement from the noiſes and more frequeent Temptations of the World, and this gave her, and me, and all that pleaſed, an happy opportunity to continue our devotions without interruption. Some Books ſhe had for contemplation, others for an Holy converſation, others for meditation, others for devotion; of all ſorts ſome, and of all theſe ſorts ſhe made ſome uſe; but of all books for conſtant uſe and practice ſhe preferred the Bible, telling me often that other Books had their uſe and delight; till with often reading they became more ordinary, and then they ſeemed to loſe of their former luſtre, glory, and excellency; but the Bible was in her often-reading ever freſh, and green, and new: She found in it ſtill ſuch per petual ſtreams of Holy, Heavenly, and Spiritual delights, that (as <hi>Teriullian</hi> ſaid) ſhe could not but <hi>admire and a dore the fulneſs of the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Ordinarily ſhe ſpent the reſt of the day in her works of the needle, with her maids a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her: Or if other things of Houſwifery had interpoſed, ſhe was never ſo tranſported with honour, as to ſcorn her duty in the way of a particular calling. Well ſhe had learnt that idleneſs was the ruſt and canker of the ſoul, the Devils cuſhion, pillow, chief repoſal, his very tide-time of Temptation; and therefore with conſcience and faithfulneſs ſhe was diligent in her particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as well as general, calling. Now and then ſhe would have viſited poor cottages, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved their neceſſities; but ever was ſhe courteous to the Neighbourhood, and careful in the affairs of her own Houſe. Take all together, and for ought I know ſhe might be a pattern to moſt of the Ladies in our Nation, or at leaſt as a bright Morning-ſtar amongſt other ſtars.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She <hi>redeemed her time</hi> in death, or near her death; now indeed ſhe was taken off her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular calling, and therefore this time ſhe ſpent (as ſhe could for ſickneſs) in the exerciſe of ſpiritual duties, and ſpiritual graces. For duties ſhe was much in them, of which we ſpeak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and for graces ſhe ſhined, and was moſt eminent in ſuch as theſe. As—</p>
            <p n="1">1. In meekneſs: She was of a meek and quiet ſpirit: ſeldome have I ſeen her exorbitant in paſſions, but often have I ſeen her amidſt provocations quiet, meek, gentle, and eaſie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated. In her ſickneſs ſhe carried it as a lamb; not a word of paſſion or peeviſhneſs iſſued out of her lips, ſo far as I obſerved. The very Image of Chriſt was, in this reſpect, drawn fair with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek: Matth.</hi> 11.29. Chriſt a meek Chriſt, and ſhe a meek creature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In humility, She was of high deſcent, and ſprung of Royal blood; yet humble in heart, and lowly in ſpirit. She never ſcorned the pooreſt Creature, but often ſtooped to wonderful condeſcentions, as I conceived. In her ſickneſs, as well as death, ſhe laid her honor in the duſt. She was far from the opinion of them that think <hi>humility a debaſement, and meekneſs a derogation from their repute;</hi> no, no, ſhe had othewiſe learned of Chriſt; humility was her Ornament, and therewith ſhe decked her ſelf (in the Apoſtles language 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.) or <hi>cloathed</hi> her ſelf, both in health and in ſickneſs, when ſhe could put on no other cloathing,. Hence ſhe was ſtiled by ſome, <hi>the humble harmleſs Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In patience, ſubmiſſion, and contentedneſs of ſpirit to be at God's diſpoſal. She had a ſore ſickneſs, and becauſe of her former health it was to her the ſorer. Of many years before ſhe had not layn ſick in Bed one day, but many a turn had ſhe took in her Walks and Gallery, and through much exerciſe in that way ſhe had the advantage both of her health and communion with God; but now the Lord laid her on a Bed of ſickneſs, not for a day, or two, or three, or four, but for a long while together. She that before had walked with God, was now God's pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner; and ſuch was the nature of the ſickneſs, that ſhe could not ſtir nor move one foot, yet was ſhe patient and ſubmiſive to God's hand; ſhe kiſſed the rod, ſhe learnt the Churches
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46544:10"/>leſſon, <hi>I will bare the indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him: Micah.</hi> 7.9. She never murmured not repined one whit, but as ſhe was taught, ſo ſhe learnt and conformed to that frame of <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>David, Lord here I am, do with me as ſeems good in thine own eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In faith. She was ever and anon, during her, ſickneſs acting faith, often ſhe acknowledged her own nothingneſs, vileneſs, wretchedneſs; that ſhe was of little faith, and of no ability, in reſpect of her ſelf, to help her ſelf. Indeed her weakneſs in faith, in grace, and in all performances was her conſtant complaint; and this made me to mind her of that promiſe, that <hi>he would not quench the ſmoaking flax, nor break the bruiſed reed, until he brought forth judgement unto victory: Mat.</hi> 12.20. Some others I have ſeen moſt confident in their ſickneſs of ſalvation, whom though I dare not cenſure, beauſe unacquainted with their grounds, yet I ingenouſly acknowledge that I like dearly of an humble, trembling, ſelf-condemning frame. Sure I am, that they who are vileſt in their own eyes, are perſons in whom God moſt delighteth. I remember how <hi>Paul</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beſpattered himſelf, but are not thoſe paſſages his beauty-pots? Give me a man amongſt you that will lick the duſt of Jeſus feet, and I dare ſay of ſuch a one, that Chriſt will take him into his armes, and lay him in his boſome: it was her condition, ſhe was all in confeſſion of her ſpiritual poverty, yet ſhe caſt her ſelf into the bleſſed-bleeding armes of Jeſus Chriſt; yea ſhe lay at his feet crying, <hi>Lord, I believe, help thou my unbelief:</hi> and again,, I <hi>reſt upon Chriſt, and upon Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone for Heaven and Salvation:</hi> and again, <hi>Though the Lord ſlay me, yet will</hi> I <hi>truſt in him:</hi> and again, <hi>He hath delivered, and he doth deliver, and</hi> I <hi>truſt in him that he will deliver me ſtill:</hi> and again, <hi>Hold out faith, and anon thou wilt come to viſion.</hi> This laſt word, <hi>hold out faith,</hi> was one of the laſt words ſhe ſpake on that laſt day of her life.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In her love to Miniſters. Her heart was wholly ſet on Chriſt; and as a true ſign of it, ſhe loved Chriſts image, eſpecially in his Miniſters. And now I ſpeak my own loſs; amongſt others ſhe was pleaſed to caſt her affections on the unworthieſt of all my Maſters meſſengers. In her life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſhe preferr'd me to this place; the Lord made her the firſt wheel of his providence in bringing me hither, and it was ſome trouble to her ſpirit that I left this paſtoral charge before ſhe left the World. Indeed ſhe honoured all the Miniſters of Chriſt, yea the very function it ſelf for Chriſt his ſake. Oh how will ſhe riſe up in judgement at the laſt day againſt thoſe that make it their work to reproach, vilifie, and contemn the diſpenſers of Gods word:</p>
            <p n="6">6. In her love and charity towards all. Many diſcords have been in theſe ſad times, and ſhe hath ſuffered much im many reſpects, yet in her approaches near to the confines of Eternity, I deſired her to forgive others, as ſhe deſired God to forgive her; at which ſhe proclamed it very affectionately, that <hi>She freely forgave all the World; and ſhe deſired all whom ſhe had offended to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give her.</hi> Her children then kneeling about her, ſhe gave them a bleſſing, as <hi>Jacob</hi> gave to <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his children: this bleſſing was pronounced with that cheerfulneſs; heartineſs, and fervency of ſpirit, that it melted hearts, and cauſed aflood of tears round about, her Bed; in ſo much that ſhe was forct to rouze up her ſelf, and to beſpeak them, as Chriſt did thoſe weeping women, <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves; why ſhould you weep for me that am going to my Chriſt, and to thoſe joyes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by Chriſt?</hi> And then ſhe gave a charge; the ſubject of it was a relative, reſpective duty to be performed by brethren; it concern'd him moſt who was <hi>the begining of her ſtrength, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of her power: Gen.</hi> 49.3. and ſo far as Juſtice, or Religion calls, I preſume it will never be forgotten by him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In her deſire to die, and to be with Jeſus Chriſt, which was beſt of all. Sometimes ſhe cried, <hi>Oh when will that good hour come!</hi> And again ſometimes, <hi>Oh that I were diſſolved, that I might be with Chriſt!</hi> But telling her of her duty, that ſhe muſt wait, for waiting was a poſture fit for ſervants; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.2. <hi>Behold as the eyes of ſervants look unto the hand of their Maſters, and as the eyes of a maiden unto the hand of her Miſtreſs, ſo our eyes wait upon the Lord our God until be have mercy upon us.</hi> Why then (ſaid ſhe) I <hi>will wait, why Lord</hi> I <hi>will wait until my change ſhall come</hi> Only ſhe minded that promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37. <hi>For yet a very little while, and he that ſhall come will come, and he will not tarry.</hi> One thing was her trouble, ſhe was afraid that her ſtrong heart would not yield without much ſtrugling to the ſtroke of death; of this ſhe told me and others once and again; her reaſons were beſt known to her ſelf, but ſhe propheſied truly; for indeed when death came to her heart, ſhe uttered ſuch groanes that ſhe outgroaned all our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. At laſt death by degrees overcame the ſtrength of nature, and then ſhe calmly and quietly left the world in the midſt of our prayers; juſt in that paſſage, that <hi>her ſoul might be taken up by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt into the Bridegroom chamber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee now how ſhe <hi>redeemed the time</hi> in life and death. As Chriſt ſaid to the Lawyer, ſo I ſay to you, <hi>Go thou and do likewiſe,</hi> Luke. 10.37. It is but a while that all of you have to live, and therfore I beſeech you improve time, lay hold of every ſeaſon to get to Heaven. <hi>Live every day as if it were your laſt on earth. Walk accurately exactly, circumſpectly, not as fools, but as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the time, becauſe the dayes are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46544:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
